<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-13T23:18:55+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Barrie Callender on my Family History</title><subtitle>I set out to find what happened to my Grandmother and discovered two sisters brutally murdered and their soldier brother losing his life on a WWI battlefield one Saturday.  I mostly write about my Jewish family history.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Where’s Grandma</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/31/wheres-grandma.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where's Grandma" /><published>2019-07-31T22:46:40+01:00</published><updated>2019-07-31T22:46:40+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/07/31/wheres-grandma</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/31/wheres-grandma.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;right-flow&quot; src=&quot;/images/1928/FH-Photo-Eva-Lichtenstein.jpg&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; alt=&quot;Eva Lichtenstein probably in 1928&quot; title=&quot;My Grandmother, Eva Lichtenstein nee Solomons, probably in 1928 when she was 21&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a photo of Eva Lichtenstein, who was my maternal Grandmother who I never met.  She is Jewish. I learned my Mum was Jewish from my Dad when I was about 9 years old.  Mum had always been too scared to mention it to anyone just in case they turned against her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was concerned when I ended up in the German half at school designating it as the foreign language for me to learn, rather than French.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Mum was 11 years old when she was evacuated from London at the start of World War 2 and was 17 when it ended in 1945.  Germany was the very last country in the world she would ever want to go to.  It was a fear she lived with all her adult life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t imagine how that felt for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now her secret was out, I was full of questions and she was full of stories and a few vague answers.  She provided quite a few short anecdotes about people and places, but Hannah Solomons, who was her Great Grandmother and her Mum, Eva Lichtenstein, were the two she missed the most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was an 8 year old girl when Hannah died in January 1937, but she last saw her Mother in 1949 and always wanted to know what happened to her.  Finding my Grandma was what started me off in Family History research, but I never applied myself as much as I could have done.  Unfortunately my Mum died in 2004 and never knew what had become of her Mother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-many-aunts-so-few-names&quot;&gt;So many Aunts, so few names?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listening to my Mum talk about her life, you would be forgiven for thinking she had many Aunties.  The truth be told she had none.  Some were Great Aunts, some other relations and I suspect some were people she respected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was the Aunt she lived with in Long Acre who witnessed a murder.  An Aunt Bessy from Prince Rupert in Canada who visited a few times, but was murdered in Prince Rupert. Another Aunt who lived in Colvestone Crescent in Dalston, often buying Lox and Cream Cheese Bagels from the Ridley Road bakery at the end of the street.  I musn’t forget the paranoid Aunt who lived south of the river as well as the one in Lambeth.  Some of these people could well be the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also had friends and occasionally gave them a name, but most people she told me about had places and stories but not names. At least not ones I remember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time my Dad announced Mum was Jewish, he also told me she had thought her name was Jacqueline Morris, which is the name on their Marriage certificate.  They found out it was Chemerofsky when they tried to emigrate to Australia.  We spent about 3 years and 3 months living in Australia but came back mostly because my Mum didn’t settle there.  She was homesick for a country where she had lost contact with her family and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Australia turned out to be traumatic due to a German family out there.  It really stressed Mum out and when our feet touched the tarmac at Gatwick, I’m sure she bent down and kissed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-little-acorns-grow-great-oaks&quot;&gt;From little acorns grow great oaks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did eventually manage to drag a few names out of Mum, did a little bit of research in the 1980s and 1990s, put it aside and got on with my life.  I tried again in 2009, but the desire wasn’t met by action.  Then various events leading up to a time in 2018 when the desire to learn more about where I came from and to actually find out where my Grandmother was took over me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have concentrated on the Jewish side and particularly the female line.  I also wanted to learn more about Jews, after all I am half-Jewish, and although I have yet to step inside a Synagogue, I feel a strong affinity with that part of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of that Journey I have read some of Simon Schama books (more than once), read My Jewish Learning site regularly, have Esther Ansell as my favourite fictional heroine and regulary read The Eternal Dissident as well as soak up information about Jewish people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I have uncovered lots of stories about my family and will try and write them up on this blog.  If you are thinking about looking into your family history, please don’t do what I did.  Please ask lots of questions of your relatives, write lots of notes and better still record conversations with them.  Try and get names and places and dates.  Ask the same question in different ways at different times.  This can trigger additional information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I seriously began my research based on the following notes, which I reproduce exactly as I wrote them on the now fading paper I still have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(1) Aunt Bessy disturbed burglars and was murdered in Prince Rupert.  Jacqueline received a letter from the commissioner of police in Prince Rupert c1949.  Bessy left her a ring in her a ring (£500) in her will.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(2) 1928 - Mark Chemerofsky, Eva Lichtenstein and Jacqueline moved to 56 Valance Road from 3 Clarkston Street.
Parliamentary Constituency: South West Division
County Electoral Division: Bethnal Green
Polling District: R
Electoral Ward: South&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(3) 1931 - Eva and Mark separated.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(4) WWII 1939 - 1945 Mark served in Fire Brigade&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(5) Alexandra Solomons killed in 1914-1918 war&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(6) Hannah Solomons died around 1937 - possibly January&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(7) The Jewish Historical Society of England
Hon Secretary 33 Seymour Place, London W1H 5AP&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(8) Ester Solomons was Eva’s mother she married Jack Lichtenstein.  Esters Mum was Hannah (See 6). Her brothers and sisters were:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Rachael Solomons = Mark Goldstein married 1944
 Jeanette Goldstein
 Gerald (b c. 1926) Goldstein&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Rebecca Solomons = Abe 
Lived in Forest Gate
 Jake&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dinah Solomons = Ike
Had a greengrocers in Hackney
 Jack
 Alex (alec)
 Kitty&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Alexandra (dur?) Solomons
Killed in 1914 - 1918 war&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Louis Solomons = ?&lt;br /&gt;
Lived in Leman street
2 daughters&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Heime Solomons = Rosie
 Helen Solomons (bit older than Mum)
 Zena Solomons&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(9) Aunt Bessy came over from Canada - had no children, looked upon Eva as daughter&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;(10) Hannah lived in Regal Place/Court No 1, Old Montague Street.  Jack lived here from 1931 onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Eva Lichtenstein also Morris
Born 1907&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Father was Jack Lichtenstein a Tailors Machinist
Mother was Esther Solomons
At the time they lived at ?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Was a milliner when married to Mark Chemerofsky on 10 June 1926.  At the time both Eva and mark lived at 45 Blythe Street, Bethnal Green.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Her daughter Jacqueline was born on 7 Feb 1928 while living at 3 Clarkson Street.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Soon after they moved to 56 Valance road and the marriage broke up with a legal separation around 1931.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;From 1949 to 1951 she lived with Alfred Purchase in Flat 13, No 9 darling Row.  She then disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Near the beginning of the war 1938-1939 she was in prison.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;hr /&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Mark Chemerofsky
Born 19 Mar 1904&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Surname spelt Shamirofsky and other phonetic connotations.
Father was Morris Schamirofsky - tailors presser later a tobacconist.
Mother was Rosie Schamirofsky formerly Levitsky.
At the time lived at 57 Wintworth Buildings, Whitechapel.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Trained as a hairdresser &amp;amp; married Eva Lichtenstein on 10 Jun 1926 when a Journeyman. At the time both Eva &amp;amp; Mark lived at 45 Blythe Street, bethnal green.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Their daughter Jacqueline was born on 7 Feb 1928 while living at 3 Clarkson Street.
Soon after they moved to 56 Vallance Road and the marriage broke up with a legal separation around 1931.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;During 2nd World War 1939-45 mark was a fireman.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Mark was a “court” hairdresser and worked for a madam Prunay? In Hackney.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began with wanting to know what happened to my Grandmother, Eva Lichtenstein, and have ended up learning far more than I expect about my Jewish family and myself.  There are still gaps and questions and although I’ve hardly begun, it’s been a roller coaster of emotion at times.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>